Finding Aid to the Katherine Gee Hornbeak papers CA.MS.00154
Smith College Archives
Katherine Gee Hornbeak papers
1772-1985
Smith College Archives
Hornbeak, Katherine Gee
CA.MS.00154
6.583 linear feet (10 containers)
Professor of English. Contains biographical material, correspondence, publications, lecture and research notes, and oversize materials.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Katherine Gee Hornbeak Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Biographical / Historical
Katherine Gee Hornbeak was Professor of English at Smith College from 1930 to 1962. She was born in Tehuacana, Texas on January 24, 1897 to Samuel L. Hornbeck and Martha Gee, one of three sisters. Her twin sister, Louise, became a professor of history and taught in Oklahoma and her sister Harriett Lee ("Hattie") (b. Aug. 1892) was a schoolteacher who taught in Panama, the Philippines and in Texas. Her father was an educator and was eventually President of Trinity University (Texas). She graduated from Trinity University in 1916 and received a master's degree from Columbia University in 1922. After her Columbia degree she taught in high schools in Cleburne, Texas and Cleveland Heights, Ohio and at the North Texas State Normal College, Denton, Texas.
Professsor Hornbeak entered Yale University where she specialized in 18th century literature and social history, in particular, the works of Samuel Richardson and Mrs. Elizabeth Montagu. Her dissertation research took her to Great Britain financed in part by a Sterling Research Fellowship. After the completion of the Ph.D. at Yale in 1930 she came to Smith College where she moved through academic ranks until she was made full professor in 1955. Professor Hornbeak was known as an exacting teacher, but one who was fair and full of praise for her students.
Among her publications are the books The Complete Letter Writer in English, 1568-1800 (1934) and Richardson's Familiar Letters and the Domestic Conduct Books (1939). Both texts were published as part of the series Smith College Studies in Modern Languages.
Professor Hornbeak retired in May 1962 and entered Smith College in the fall of that year as a special student in order to study the Greek language, a study that continued for a number of years. Her studies brought her the Julia Harwood Caverno Prize in May 1964, a prize usually awarded to a member of the junior or senior class for excellent in Greek language and literature. She gained such proficiency that she was called upon to teach Greek as a lecturer at Smith College in 1965/1966.
The retreat owned by Smith College, Juniper Lodge, Silver Lake, New Hampshire was often her summer residence during her early years at Smith and for many years she served as the chair of its executive committee. Professor Hornbeck died on February 24, 1985.
Related Material
Researchers should also view:
52. Smith College Department of English Records
"Katherine Hornbeak," Smith Alumnae Quarterly, Summer 1985, p. 68-69.
Scope and Contents
The Katherine Gee Hornbeak Papers contain items related to Professor Hornbeak's affiliation with Smith College and her own education. There is extensive correspondence from her sisters Harriett Lee Hornbeak ("Hattie") and Louise Hornbeak. In addition there is correspondence with Ruth Hillyer Hill, Katherine Strayer and Anne Francis (Smith College, M.A., 1942; Headmistress of the Pontypool Girls' County School, Penygarn, Wales, 1945-1960s) and from various students and friends.
Professor Hornbeak's research and lecture notes reflect a teacher's use and reuse of notes throughout her teaching career. A file may contain notes for a particular course in a given year, but it is more apt to contain notes from a succession of years (sometimes dated to show succession). Folders labels suggest a date for a course as noted by Hornbeak but materials included may reflect a range of dates. Also there are situations where a particular file will include papers related to more than one course number. Duplication between files does occur and notes on a particular topic may appear in more than one file. For the most part files are as Professor Hornbeak left them and reflect these many apparent date and course conflicts.
The Hornbeak papers are divided into four series:
Series I: General materials (1930s-1985)
Series II: Correspondence (1916-1985)
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Lecture and research notes
Series V: Oversize materials
Hornbeak, Katherine Gee
- Series I - General
  - Biographical materials, 1985; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address books, Christmas card lists, etc., 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial papers, 1930s-1960s; 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Call slips from a British library, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, some of Hornbeak, others not identified, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph album - snapshots of Colorado (?), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photograph album - snapshots of New Hampshire and New England, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Retirement items, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificate from Trinity University (Texas) "upon the fiftieth anniversary of [K.G.H.'s] graduation", May 30, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8a)
  - KGH's Greek studies-Student papers and related documents, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8b)
  - Greek 11 Examinations and papers, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8c)
  - Greek studies-Drafts of articles on, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8d)
  - Family documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hornbeak's written examination for Yale University's English 123-Shakespeare for Professor C. B. Tinker, January 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  - Yale University Commencement program and related material, June 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9b)
  - Miscellaneous materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - European travel pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II - Correspondence
  - Correspondence from Katherine G. Hornbeak, 1945-1946; 1955-1979; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Katherine G. Hornbeak to Ruth Hillyer Hill
    - June 1929-Sep 1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Oct 1929-Dec 1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Jan 1930-Aug 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Ruth Hillyer Hill, July 1929-Dec 1929 (Box 2, Folder 5a)
  - Correspondence from Ruth Hillyer Hill, 1931-1932; 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5b)
  - Correspondence from Katherine Strayer, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from Priscilla Presbrey, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from Priscilla Presbrey, 1929-1932; undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Christmas letters from Katherine G. Hornbeak, 1949-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from Lois Ames, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Samuel L. Hornbeak ("Father"), 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 10a)
  - Correspondence from "Pattie", 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10b)
  - Correspondence from Harriett Lee Hornbeak (Hattie) to Lona and Ruth Spruiell with occasional correspondence to Mrs. W. P. Withers (Carrie) from Harriett Hornbeak, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from Harriett Lee Hornbeak ("Hattie") to Katherine Hornbeak ("Tassie")
    - n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Feb 1969-Apr 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Aug 1969-Dec 1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Jan 1970-May 1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - June 1970-Dec 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Jan 1971-Aug 1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Sep 1971-Dec 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Jan 1972-May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - June 1972-Dec 1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Jan 1973-June 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - July 1973-Dec 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - 1974 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence from Louise Hornbeak ("Lub") to Katherine G. Hornbeak ("Tod"), 1935-1985 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence from Katherine G. Hornbeak to Anne Francis, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence from Anne Francis to Katherine G. Hornbeak, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence from Anne Francis to Katherine G. Hornbeak, 1945-1981 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence from and related to Cuthbert Becher Pigot, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 29a)
  - Correspondence from C. B. Tinker and Remarks on C.B. Tinker and the 18th Century at a dinner Jan 18, 1947, 1944-1949 (Box 4, Folder 29b)
  - Correspondence from Jane Shaw, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 29c)
  - Correspondence from Dorothy Robinson, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 29d)
  - Correspondence from Jean Hecht, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 29e)
  - Correspondence from W. Douglas Simpson, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 29f)
  - Correspondence from Arthur Raistrick, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 29g)
  - Correspondence with the Duke of Northumberland, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 29h)
  - Correspondence from Diana Gould White, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence from Virginia Corwin Brautigam and Herman A. Brautigam, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence from and related to Marjorie Hanson, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence from Betty Baum, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence from various individuals (usually only one item from each individual), some identified only by first name, Christmas greetings
    - 1928-1964 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - 1972-1984 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - n.d. (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence from Trinity University (Texas) officials, 1916-1922 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence from North Texas State Normal College, Denton, Texas officials, 1922-1924 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence from Cleburne Public Schools, Cleburne, Texas official, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence from Cleveland Heights Schools, Ohio official, 1926-1929 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence from Yale University officials, 1927-1979 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Series III - Publications
  - Publications, 1949-1966 (Box 5)
- Series IV - Lecture and research notes
  - English honors examinations-Notes, etc. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lecture notes for English 11-Notes, etc. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - English 19-Notes, etc. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - English 19-Examinations and notes (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lecture notes for English 21 and syllabi (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Examinations and notes for English 21 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Lecture notes on Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bunyan memorabilia (post cards, booklets, etc.), 1960s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Lecture notes on Congreve's The Way of the World (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Lecture notes on Milton (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Lecture notes on Milton's Paradise Lost (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Lecture notes on Fielding's Joseph Andrews (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Fielding and Fielding's Tom Jones (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Lecture notes on Pope's Rape of the Lock (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Notes on the [Royal] Game of Ombre (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Notes on Pope (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Notes on Pope's Essay on Man to Gen. Lit. 291 in Sage Hall, March 13, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Pope and Swift as satirists (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Notes on Swift [1] (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Notes on Swift [2] (satire) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Lecture notes on Richardson (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Notes on Keats (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Comedies-English 21 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Notes, etc. for English 29 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Notes on Medieval drama (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Lecture notes for English 40b-18th Century, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Notes for English 58-Boswell and Johnson, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Notes for English 58-18th Century, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Notes for English 58-18th Century, 1945-1950 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Lecture notes for English 58a-18th Century, 1950/1951 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Lecture notes for English 58a-18th Century, 1951/1952 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Lecture notes for English 58a, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Lecture notes for English 310, Spring Semester 1949 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - K.G.H.'s letter and questionnaire to English 310 students, June 9, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Lecture notes for English 310, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Reading period lists, English 310, 1947-1955 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Examinations, English 310, 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Bibliographies on the Social Background of the 18th Century, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Notes on Mandeville and Shaftesbury (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Satire-Definitions of terms-Survey of 17th and 18th century dictionaries (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Satire-General Notes (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Satire lecture notes, English 310a, 1939-1943 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Satire lecture notes, English 310a (1), 1946-1951 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Satire lecture notes, English 310a (2), 1946-1951 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Satire lecture notes, English 310a, 1953-1958 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Satire lecture notes, English 310a, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Satire lecture notes and syllabi, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Student cards-English 310a, 1962 (?) (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Lecture notes for English 310a (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Examinations, English 310a (some for English 310), 1930s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Examinations, English 310a, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Suggestions for term papers, English 310a and English 310b (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Notes on Petronius (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Notes on Erasmus and Rabelais (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Notes on Lucian (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Johnson as literary critic-English 310a and 310b (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Johnson as literary critic-English 310b-Student assignment (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Johnsonon (various topics) (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Lecture notes on Huxley, Waugh and Orwell (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Reserve book list for English 310a and Roman satire materials, Latin 34b, 1953-1958 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Wit and burlesque notes (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - "Splitting the infinitive" notes (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Notes on Don Quixote (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Don Quixote illustrations, including Horst Lemke's (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Notes on Sentimentalism and Richardson (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Notes on Sentimental comedy 18th Century (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Syllabi for English 310b, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Reading period and library reserve reading lists for English 310b (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Examinations, English 310b, 1930s-1960s (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Memo book for English 310b, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Lecture notes for English 310b-Boswell and Johnson, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Outline and lecture notes for English 310b, 1940s-1960s (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Lecture notes for English 310b, 1957-1961 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Lecture notes and/or syllabi, English 310b, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous notes for English 310b (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Map study, English 310b-18th Century London (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - 18th Century London-Maps (Glass slides) (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Notes on friendship and women (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Notes on Addison and Steele (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Notes on Defoe (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Notes on Dryden (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Notes on Macpherson's Ossian (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Notes on Gray (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Notes on Gentleman's Magazine (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Notes on Goldsmith (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Notes on James Thomson [1] (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Notes on James Thomson [2] (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Notes on Mary Astell (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Notes on Rambler and Idler-17th and 18th Century journalism-English 310b, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Notes on Juvenal and Johnson, English 310b (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Social background of the age of Johnson (notes on) (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Lecture notes on Boswell and Johnson (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Notes on Boswell's Life of Johnson (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Notes on Boswell as biographer (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Notes and lecture notes on Johnson's Dictionary (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Photographs and illustrations of Johnson and Johnsonian sites (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Notes on Rasselas and Candide, English 59 and English 310b, 1940s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Notes on P. H. Houston's Dr. Johnson (1923), 1930s (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Notes for talk on the literary scene in England, 1761, April 1961 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Notes on Boswell's papers (general) (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Notes on Boswell's papers, v. 1-6 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Notes on Boswell's papers, v. 8-12 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Notes on Boswell's papers, v. 13-15 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Clippings on Boswell's London journal, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Clippings on Boswell's papers, 1948-1950 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Clippings on Johnson and Boswell, 1930s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Satire unit student papers, undated (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Satire unit student papers [1], 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Satire unit student papers [2], 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Satire unit student papers, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Satire unit student papers [1], 1959 (Box 8, Folder 111)
  - Satire unit student papers [2], 1959 (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Satire unit student papers [3], 1959 (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Irene Levy paper (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Marian Allison McCrillis paper, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - Mary-Elizabeth Bruce paper, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - Katherine Reese paper, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Notes on Peacock and Bryon (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - Notes for English 314-English Novel (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Notes for English 414 a and b, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Notes for English 414 a and b, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Notes on Sir Robert Walpole and for English 414b, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Notes on diaries (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Notes on biography (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - Notes on domestic handbooks-Yale University Library, Summer 1931 (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Notes on women and domestic relationships (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Samples of and/or for examinations in English literature, 1940s-1950s (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Notes on, drafts and letters of recommendation, 1950s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - K.G.H.'s personal files on Smith College's M.A. in English literature
    - 1952-1953/1954 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - 1954/1955 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - [1] 1955/1956 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - [2]1956 (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - K.G.H.'s copy of Newton Arvin's "The Grounds of Literary Judgment" (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Notes on lecture by Elizabeth Drew, "Life and art in the novel"-Sage Hall, Oct. 5, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - Research on the letters of Lady Mary Wortley Montagu
    - Correspondence from and to K.G.H. related to the Montagu letters, 1938-1953 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Notes on Montagu letters
      - [1] (Box 8, Folder 136)
      - [2] (Box 8, Folder 137)
      - [3] (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - Newspaper clippings on Montagu biographies and criticism (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - Note cards on various subjects (Box 9)
- Series V: Oversize
  - Lithograph of cats, by Jim Sekim (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Reproduction of the "View of the interior of the Rotunda at Ranelgh," by Caneletto from the National Gallery (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Photostat of letter of Lady Elizabeth Montagu, Sept. 4, 1772 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Photostat of will of Lady Elizabeth Montagu, August 27, 1809 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Photostat of documents 18th century (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Reproductions of etchings and paintings of 18th Century England (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "18th Century England"-article in Life, Sept. 13, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 7)